<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An entertainment of solitarinesse or, the melting of the soule, by meditations, and the pouring of it out by prayers. By Sir Richard Tempest, knight and baronet.</title>
            <author>Tempest, Richard, Sir, 1619 or 20-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74649</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1410_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209519</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868395</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868395</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169925</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74649)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169925)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 181:E1410[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An entertainment of solitarinesse or, the melting of the soule, by meditations, and the pouring of it out by prayers. By Sir Richard Tempest, knight and baronet.</title>
                  <author>Tempest, Richard, Sir, 1619 or 20-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 142, [2] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Meditation --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:169925:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:169925:2"/>
            <head>Qui violat Roſam, ſpinis Coronabitur.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>crowned Tudor rose</figDesc>
                  <q>Qui Violat Roſam, Spinis Coronabitur.</q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Sanguine ſub nimiâ languet, Roſa tincta colore</l>
                     <l>ſic luget proprio; purpurat ora rubor:</l>
                     <l>En! Phoebi reditum madeſacta liquore precatur</l>
                     <l>ſub Caroli radiis ut micet illa ſui.</l>
                  </q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169925:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Entertainment OF Solitarineſſe: <hi>OR,</hi> The Melting of the SOULE, by <hi>Meditations,</hi> and the pouring of it out by <hi>Prayers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Sir RICHARD TEMPEST, Knight and Baronet.</p>
            <q>—Sine me liber ibis in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbem.</q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169925:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169925:3"/>
            <head>TO His deare Brothers, <hi>Nicholas Tempest,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Tempeſt,</hi> Eſquires.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Deare Brothers,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN you I have enjoyed the happy freedoms and privileges of friendſhip which conſociate the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt regions of mens hearts with the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of their mutuall thoughts. I communicate to you now theſe Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (the Companions of my ſolitarineſſe) that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:169925:4"/> the Preſſe is debaucht, yet by the quick paſſage of it, you might participate of my thoughts at this diſtance; whereby in part I might turne my Loneneſſe into Companie and Converſation. And though the accidents of the time have violently ſnatcht you from me, whereby you have chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your freedome for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint; yet all the unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing paſſages of <hi>Fortune,</hi> or her moſt plauſible Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips work nothing upon
<pb facs="tcp:169925:4"/> a mind, ſeated on that firm reſolution, to be true to GOD, the King, and his friend the very Heathen could ſay, Commit thy ſelf to an honeſt &amp; juſt action, as to a tutelar God. Thoſe minds alone that are not raiſed above the trifles and vanities of the world, feele the tyranny of paſsion and adverſitie; others, who lie not levell with its injuries, carry a happineſſe in their owne breſts, which tents as it were, they can ſet down in any condition or
<pb facs="tcp:169925:5"/> place, &amp; be happy in Saint <hi>Paul</hi> named no one ſtate wherein he could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; but had learned, in what ſtate ſoever, to be content: &amp; certainly, ſuch a ſtate of mind onely as is agreeable to the traverſes of the world, conſidering every thing as it is in its own alterable nature, and withall making uſe of the prerogative of the Soule, which is above any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thing, can fix or ſettle in mans life a felicitie, which all men ſo earneſtly court,
<pb facs="tcp:169925:5"/> and ſo few obtaine; many preſenting their ſervice to that Miſtris of all mens Soules, out of vainglory, or covetouſneſſe, or worldly intereſt; ſhe being the moſt quick-ſighted Lady, which will not confer her favors on any, but who are truly inamored with it ſelf; God himſelf being that eſſential Aeternitie, who is alone to be loved for himſelfe.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q xml:lang="ita">Queſtò e il vero geiore che naſce dà virtu dopò il ſoffrire.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 20. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your faithfull Brother, <hi>Rich: Tempeſt.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169925:6"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>HE who ſacrificeth his Vertue to the <hi>genius</hi> of the Times, ſhall find its favours not ſo durable, as the reward of his Vice is certaine; one may goe ſmiling, or feareleſſe, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; the affections of deceived minds, change nothing the nature of the evils incurred; there is a fixt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable nature of good, which acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of fortune and events commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable to good or bad actions, cannot change nor ſubvert: ſucceſſe dazles the vulgar eye; and minds that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke the ſervice of Vertue, for the love they bare its rewards, no longer adore the beautie of the other, than their lower minds are bribed with the pettie ſatisfactions to their inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or intereſts. Its the moſt contemptible ſlaverie of the mind, to pin its value and eſteeme of justice upon the ſleeve of fortune; there being nothing truly
<pb facs="tcp:169925:6"/> fixt and permanent, but ſacred Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, which men ſo readily forſake for every thing that of its ſelfe naturally makes progreſſe to change (a neceſſary mutabilitie and alteration adhering to the nature of all other things.) By the communication of theſe thoughts, the times are not courted, chuſing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to dote upon the foame falling from the jawes of <hi>Cerberus;</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as <hi>Tacitus</hi> notes ſometime to happen out, wherein is a certain ruine for thoſe who hold with dutie; and wherein one might juſtly reſume the demand of that Orator, who being applauded by the vulgar, asked his friend, what ill he had ſpoke? Theſe papers chuſe rather to be as miſerable as ever the merry Poets could make any, by their threatned judgements and wittie condemnations, <hi>aut piper aut thus.</hi> It will be a loathſome thing to ſtay behind all that, to which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction is threatned; when as with all their proteſtations, pecuniarie and
<pb facs="tcp:169925:7"/> ſanguinarie prodigalitie, in ſtead of bringing home the Golden Fleece, which is that addition of Wealth, Honour, and Power, to the King and his people, they have onely uſed them all as means to make them moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, by the deſtroying of what is glorious and worthy. The Kingdome is touched (as I may ſay) with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy: and though the Needle is by a violent hand ſet to contrarie Pointe of the Compas, and by the contrarie winds of Factions they attempt to ſail to <hi>Utopian</hi> &amp; fancied Governments yet <hi>uſque recurret,</hi> the Needle will not ſtand but to its beloved Pole. All miſerable practiſes upon the health<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full conſtitution of our dear Mother. But alas! who would grieve truly for thee, muſt let his veines bleed purple teares, to deliver thy tender breſts deareſt Mother, from the desperate hands of thy cruell and bloudie exe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cutioners.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169925:7"/>
            <head>The melting of the SOULE, &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="essay">
               <head>On Sundayes, Holy dayes, and Fasting dayes.</head>
               <p>HEE whoſe mind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Reaſon, and Religion, orders his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward obſervances ſo, that they may be the tranſitorie Hieroglyphicks of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward pietie. They are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly Devotions, which neglect the Injunctions of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169925:8"/> the Church, concerning the time, place, and manner of them: ſince every action is inveſted with ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and hath ſuch for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities annext to them, the gravitie and ſolemnitie of enjoyned Ceremonie will ſuite better with regular zeales, than the garbes and formes privat fancies would put on them.</p>
               <p>Thy holy Word, O Lord, is the Sunne, which by caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its beames on the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures and diſtinctions of the Churches Dyall, points out and orders to us the times of our lives.</p>
               <p>Some Religions weare onely the finer Liverie of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169925:8"/> Sundayes, others love to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare attended with the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der traine of Faſting dayes. When I conſult with the Church, I finde both enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and when I adviſe with my owne nature, I find them ſuited to the two principall affections in man, Joy, and Griefe: Let not my ſervice of thee, O Lord, be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhapen in its parts; but what I doe to pleaſe thee, let it be guided by thee.</p>
               <p>There is ſuch a confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie betweene the ſoule and the body, they doe ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually operate one upon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, that even thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints put upon our appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, quicken and make
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169925:9"/> active the motions of the ſoule: for when the body its organ is diſtempered, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torts and ſhoots backward its indiſpoſitions to the minde; (our thoughts ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times condenſed into the corporeall delights of the ſenſe; ſometimes rarified into the pure abſtracted pleaſures of the ſpirit.)</p>
               <p>And ſince bodily abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence aides and contributes aptitude to the mind, for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viner receptions; let me follow the wiſdome of thy methods, Lord, who by the Churches directions, of their Faſts to precede our Feſtivals, teacheth us, humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie goes before glory, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169925:9"/> and mortification before true joy.</p>
               <p>But now, alas! the outward and materiall Temples are made to mourn in their own aſhes, <hi>while the living ones rejoyce over the ruines of Sion.</hi> The looſeneſſes and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences of this Age, rather beares a proportion with the Religion of the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> than exhibits Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces pleaſing to the moſt Holy One. They caſhiering all ſtrict obſervances, as fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and bonds to their more free <hi>Genius,</hi> are miſ-led by their owne evill ſpirits in a wilderneſſe of Opinions.</p>
               <p>The obſerving theſe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall dayes, turnes our devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169925:10"/> into the knowne and vulgar Character, which the world by our practiſe (as it were) may reade. Our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie charges the Times with good or bad events happening in them; not but thoſe good or ill qualities adhere to the things done in thoſe Times, (Time being onely the meaſure of moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) upon whoſe skore wee retaine the remembrance of what things pleaſing, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing, have befallen us.</p>
               <p>To quarrell at the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Times, is to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell at the holy and devout Exerciſes at ſuch times uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally performed; whence wee ſee ſo eaſie a ſlide in many,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169925:10"/> from the contempt of the time, to neglect the humble and pious practiſes of the other: To take away the ſet Dayes, ſet Prayers, and ſet Patrimonie of the Church, is to make the Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, their lives diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, and their devotions prophane.</p>
               <p>The Magnificats of hearts, divinely in love, and the heavenly wealth of an open-handed Charitie, makes theſe dayes proſpect ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; and in this reſpect, they are inlightned with no vulgar Ray, nor doth the Sunne ſhine with any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon beames.</p>
               <p>The Heathens marked
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169925:11"/> their fortunate dayes with white, or precious ſtones; but wee muſt obſerve theſe with white and ſpotleſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, by which they will prove ſo to us: Our miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Times we becloud either over againe with our griefes, and diſtruſts, or elſe adde to them the feathers of vanitie, to make them more inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly flye away; (the two exceſſes of our life) too jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Vanities, or too ſad Dejections.</p>
               <p>But from the heights of theſe dayes, doe our ſoules take their Aethereall flights, and range them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Quires of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, while they beare part
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169925:11"/> with them, in their <hi>Allelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jahs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord grant, that by the continued practiſe of theſe Heavenly Attempts, the chayne of my mortalitie being broke, I may get wing, and flye to thee; and that conſtantly reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my hands to thee from theſe dayes, which are the upper ſteps of the Ladder of my Life, next to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, thou mayeſt at laſt reach forth thy hand, and receive me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:169925:12"/>
               <head>Morning Thoughts.</head>
               <p>DArkeneſſe no ſooner gives way to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the Sunne, but the whole Theatre of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſeemes to ſmile; the Clouds put on their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall-coloured Habits; the Muſicall inhabitants of the Groves warble forth the Aire in varied and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tones of harmonie; the Flowers draw forth their ſeverall flames and beauties, offering ſweet incenſe from their fragrant boſomes; all miſts and fogges breake up and vaniſh; and that which before diſſembled ſo bright
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169925:12"/> a luſtre, hath loſt it in the light of the Sunne. And now my ſenſes looſned from the ſoft chaines of ſleepe, enjoy the proſpect of the glory of the Heavens, the pleaſant view of the Woods, Fields, Rivers: but as there be Groves, and Caves, where the Sunne hath not acceſſe; ſo my Body is that Cave, where, without the beame of Reaſon, to diſcerne the cauſes and effects of thoſe works I externally behold, it is ſtill in darkneſſe; nay, I ſhall ſtill continue ſo, if with the reflext beame of Reaſon I looke not into my ſelfe, and ſee what habits and affections my Soule
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169925:13"/> weares, and what belongs to me, in reſpect of duties and ſeverall relations without: nay, I am ſtill in darkneſſe, if I behold not with the eye of Faith the Sonne of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe ariſing (as it were) out of the immenſe Ocean of his Goodneſſe and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, darting into my Soule the glorious rayes of his Truth and Goodneſſe; then doth my little World re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and my fleſh rejoyces in the living Lord; then are all my affections, the Birds in my little Grove, tuned with his prayſe; then doth each thought weare a ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Liverie of its Makers prayſe, put on from the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169925:13"/> contemplation of his ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall workes; then are all the falſe ſplendors of Vanitie obſcured, the miſts and fogges of Paſſion breake up and vaniſh; then doe the flowers of Vertue ſalute him with that luſtre and odour he himſelfe beſtowed on them; ſome yeelding their ſweets at a diſtance, as the tender Vertues of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, Compaſſion, Liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; others impart not their fragrancie, till bruiſed and cruſhed, as the Vertues of Patience, and Conſtancie: And now, Lord, my impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd Soule beholds thy beames, through the chinks as it were of thy Creatures;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169925:14"/> but a full viſion of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is reſerved for the ſtate of Glory.</p>
               <p>Let my mind ſo feed on thy Workes, that they be diſgeſted into thy prayſe; and let me looke out ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly through theſe Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, at the rayes of thy Goodneſſe, Wiſdome, and Power, that at laſt my ſpark may be ſwallowed up in the immenſitie of thy light.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <head>Evening Thoughts.</head>
               <p>HEavens ſable Curtaines being dtawn, Darkneſſe makes all things alike: the feather'd Muſicians of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169925:14"/> Wood repoſe their aeriall ſpirits amidſt the leavie Groves; a ſilent horror ſeemes to poſſeſſe all places, while thoſe Silver-footed Nymphs, that by ſo many windings arrive at the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie armes of <hi>Neptune,</hi> ſend forth their pleaſant mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mures louder, not drowned with greater noyſe: if the Sunne hath ſet in a Cloud, it hath preſaged ſtormes to the enſuing day.</p>
               <p>I finde a reſemblance in my leſſer World, of Nights Liverie, when I winke the World into Darkneſſe; by which, all beauties loſe their diſtinctions; all lye lovingly together in the boſome of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169925:15"/> ſleepe, and agree in their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to theſe ſoft in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions, and delightfull commands of Nature. Here the Miſer is pleaſantly robd of his ſtore, and the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man of his ſenſe of being poore. The ambitious man leaves to court Greatneſſe, and is content with the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie favours of <hi>Morpheus:</hi> the Lover layes aſide the ſweet tortures of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and ſolaces himſelfe only in the duskie imbraces of ſleepe: the Souldier, in making his paſſage to the gates of vocall Fame, ceaſes to invite Death, and is here content with its image.</p>
               <p>Now doe our ſenſes, which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169925:15"/> are the Birds that make the Muſick in mans little Grove, ſhrowd themſelves under the downie wings of ſleepe. Thus doth Death e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualize all things onely for a longer time; in its habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations a quiet horror ſeems to dwell, where all lye lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly in the boſome of their Mother Earth, ſilently crept under the ſoft Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Aſhes; where our divided parts revell in their looſened motions, which had before beene crowded together in our ſickly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſures. I lye merrily down in my Bed, though I expect to riſe againe, to reſume the burthen of all my feares,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169925:16"/> hopes, and griefes, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant attendants of my life; and yet looke ſadly and mournfully upon the Grave, my corruption belonging to the maintaining of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Univerſe; where, at my next riſing, much gayer clad then before, I ſhall awake to immortalitie and endleſſe joy: with the eye of Reaſon I can looke through the glory of the world, and behold Vanitie, and Oblivion; with the eye of Faith I can look through Oblivion and Corruption it ſelfe, and behold Glory and Eternitie. Now I finde, how many things doe not (that are eſteemed in popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169925:16"/> judgements to) make one happy; how little they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute towards it, to me alone, till I be mixt with thoſe people, and take pleaſure in thoſe Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>We entertaine with true and reall paſſions the Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall compoſitions of the Stage; there being in mans life Playes, not acted, but li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; ſolemne fictions, not feigned, but beleeved. Men now acknowledge their own Natures, whom Precept had taught to regulate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves all day, and familiarly owne the impreſſions Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath charactered on them.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:169925:17"/>
               <p>Now doth the ever-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtreames of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, which run over our hard and ſtonie hearts, ſpeak louder to us, not drowned with the noyſe of worldly thoughts. If the Sunne hath gone downe in the clouds of our envie and malice, it preſages future ſtormes of paſſions to our life.</p>
               <p>And now, Lord, I will ſeeke him in my Bed, whom my Soule loves: Let me finde thee, in the reſt thou giveſt my Soule from Sinne and Vanity, in the ſleep thou giveſt my affections, they being all quietly repoſed in thee; and thus I reſt on thee, more than on where I lye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:169925:17"/>
               <head>The Arraignment of the Heart.</head>
               <p>I Thought I had ſo well ſurveyed this little piece of Earth, that I had knowne every turning and winding in it: but, ſince I had a holy purpoſe betray'd to ſome eaſie temptation, I ſuſpected that there was ſomething yet undiſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Whereupon, calling my Travell, Studie, and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation thither, I found a ſtrange Labyrinth, which the thred of my Reaſon was too ſhort to unwinde me out of; I found it ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circled with the Serpentine
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169925:18"/> windings of Sinne, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed with thoſe flexu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous imbraces, that I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Vanitie entring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduct of its adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, apt to glory in the contempt of Glory, and grow proud in the loweſt debaſing my ſelfe: and upon demand of Reaſon for any good, it would informe me, That it owed its originall to ſome ſecret paſſion, which would untitle it againe.</p>
               <p>There is nothing but darkeneſſe, and wandrings, here; ſo that I perceive, O Lord, I was more ſecure than ſafe, ſince I lodged here ſuch deceitfull gueſts, that anſwered at the light knock
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169925:18"/> of every idle paſſion. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to have diſcovered my heart to thee, but found it firſt neceſſarie, that thou ſhouldſt diſcover it to me; where was ſuch a wilderneſſe of Paſſions, ſuch rocks of Pride, ſuch <hi>Maeanders</hi> of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, and perplext paths of contradictorie motions, that it mockt my paſt endevours, and taught me to know, that other things might be in the light to me, yet I in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to my ſelfe. And ſince thy ſacred Spirit hath dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to me, that it is deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately wicked and inſcruta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I arraigne it before thy Throne, as that corrupt Fountaine, whence hath
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169925:19"/> flowed thoſe bitter ſtreames of Vanitie, which hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed my life; and here, where my naturall life firſt begins, my ſpirituall death firſt ariſes. I begge of thee, my God, another Creation, firſt, of a cleane heart; and that then thy ſacred Spirit would move upon the face of theſe waters, and forme this <hi>Chaos</hi> into that beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and order, where thou wouldſt have thy own Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Wiſdome manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: breathe forth thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Light into my Soule, and to the conſiderations of my heart, cauſe a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betweene the Night of Sinne, to be feared; and the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169925:19"/> Light of Truth, to be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; make a ſeparation in me, betwixt heavenly and earthly thoughts; let the other be ſuperior and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant over theſe; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all here into forme and fruitfulneſſe; plant the flowers of vertue, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fed with the Manna-drops of thy Grace, they may communicate their gratefull properties of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and odour to others: Cauſe the Lights thou haſt ſet in my little World, to ſhine clearer, that every of them may have their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and proper influences upon the courſe of my life: When the Sunne of thy
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169925:20"/> Word ſhines out, let all other Lights be obſcured; however, let that thy other Light of Reaſon rule the darker part of my life; let the leſſer Lights of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (whoſe motions, though they be erratique, yet doe operate upon our actions) keepe ſuch place and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that they hinder not the generall harmonie of the Fabrick. That part which denominates my <hi>Species,</hi> make new in me; that part formed after thy owne I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; and give it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over the beaſts of the field, that Reaſon may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the wildneſſe of my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. And now, Lord,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169925:20"/> let all the motions of this Piece turne upon the poles of thy Commands; let it be centred in the obedience to thy will, that there it may finde a conſtant Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and Reſt. This is the regeneration of this leſſer World; element it, Lord, with the fire of thy heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly love, ſurround it with the holy breathings of thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit: Let conſtancie and ſolid fixneſſe be in my wayes, let the current of all my thoughts emptie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Ocean of the infinitie of thy goodneſſe and glory: And yet, Lord, this World could not ſtand a moment, if thou didſt not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169925:21"/> behold it through thy Son. Its the deſire of my heart to entertaine thee: as thou art the author of that deſire, be thou alſo the granter of it. I know, a heart being fill'd with any thing, denyes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to another; I am full of my ſelfe, grant me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie my ſelfe, to be emptied of my ſelfe: for here it is, that the pleaſures and trifles of the World hold intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and correſpondence, in themſelves not ſo forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but as they flatter my underſtanding, or affection, with apt pretences.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Perſeus</hi> in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition was to kill the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, he had a Looking-Glaſſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169925:21"/> given him, wherein he was to behold the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, as he ſhould ſtrike at him, and not to looke upon it ſelfe; and we ſhall kill the Serpents of outward temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, if we looke at their figures, preſented in the Glaſſe of our thoughts, and there deſtroy them in their images, received in our hearts.</p>
               <p>Lord, doe thou poſſeſſe my heart, that it may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe thee; that it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thee, receive it; thou art within all things, not included: let me finde thy infinite Power, in the exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thy Mercie, and not in thy Juſtice; let me put
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169925:22"/> off my ſelfe: my ſelfe, is my wayes, my cuſtomes, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; thy promiſe is, for protecting us in thy wayes. When I ſeeke to have my own image repreſented back again to me more beautifull from the Glaſſe of popular Opinions, courting Fame, or Applauſe; when I for feare or flatterie neglect to doe my dutie to thee my God, or man, then am I in my owne wayes, ſeeking Death in the errors of my life. I give thee, Lord, that one ſyllable thou deſireſt, my (heart;) begging the exchange of another for it (Love:) But becauſe I am a very bubble, which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169925:22"/> it be blowne into ſome curious-coloured He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſphere, by ſome good inſpirations, yet the leaſt ruffling winde from abroad makes evaporate: And though I be wound up to ſome holy reſolutions by the finger of thy Spirit, yet without thy conſtant aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, I ſhould relapſe, and fall into looſeneſſe and dejectedneſſe; therefore I begge of thee my Heart againe, that thou wouldeſt before the conveyance of it paſſe, give it me under the cuſtodie of thy Grace, ſealed up by thy bleſſed Spirit, that no ſinfull Paſſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, nor outward Glory, nor
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169925:23"/> Beautie, the ſolliciters of Vanitie, doe ever breake it up.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <head>Deceit doth debaſe our Nature, and falſe Policie deſtroy Governments.</head>
               <p>MAn, that Noble Coyne, which bears the Image of the King of Heaven, is ſo debaſed with the alloy of his owne imaginations, that it will not paſſe. Lord, thou art one undivided ſimple eſſence, and requireſt Truth in the inward parts, and ſpirits, wherein there is no guile: Wherefore thou haſt taught us, that under the forme of Children, wee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169925:23"/> the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; by the revocation of which innocent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible part of our lives, the value is brought downe of all thoſe falſe Wares men have fraughted their mindes with, in the voyage of this life; thoſe falſe O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, deluded Affections, which doe create to men their joyes and feares. Wee ſhall finde, Deceit hath underminded all the little ſtructures of Delight men have builded out of Fancie, while Opinions are enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Soule, which beare not the lawfull im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Truth, but the counterfeit ſtampe of their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169925:24"/> owne affection. Truth is the onely firme <hi>Baſis</hi> of mans content and happineſſe, the images of the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as they be in their owne natures, received as it were into the Glaſſe of the mind; ſettle there that which we call Truth, when there is a conformitie betwixt the things and our minds: but when man vitiates and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorts his mind with wrong and erronious apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe things, then are our mindes a Magick Glaſſe, which ſhewes us the images of things that are not. Thus are mens griefes Panique, and their joyes perſonate.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:169925:24"/>
               <p>Thoſe teares of <hi>Alexander</hi> were as ridiculous, which the report of another part of the World yet uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, drew from him, as of that poore woman, whom the Philoſopher ſaw weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for her Pitcher ſhe had broke.</p>
               <p>Man mingling his decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved conceptions with the things themſelves, frights himſelfe with that Vizard hee himſelfe beſtowes on things, which in themſelves are naturall, orderly, and neceſſarie. Waters that at the Fountaine head are pure and ſweetly taſted, in their ſubterraneous paſſage beget new and foraine taſts. What
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169925:25"/> a Maze doth humane nature tread in? How many are the Cozenages of his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Man, as it were in the Tyring-roome of his fancie, beſtowes his ſeverall Dreſſes and Attires on things, which he on the Stage of the world really counts for ſuch as he hath cloathed them for. Thus are all things made to beare the Liverie of his imaginations, and are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted back againe into the affections, according to the richneſſe of the habits hee made them fine with.</p>
               <p>Folly, ſaith <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> heares it ſelfe ill ſpoke of even amongſt the moſt fooliſh: and many would entertaine
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169925:25"/> with laughter the ſtorie of that foole, who leapt and danced, becauſe he thought all the ſhips that came into the harbour were his owne; when perhaps no leſſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall would their owne Mirths prove, which are drawne (perhaps) from the eſteeme of ſome things, which ſerve to make a great part of their lives ſeeme pleaſant to them, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their worth viewed in the light of Reaſon, would be found not ſufficient to yeeld ſuch a warmth and influence, to warme or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create their deluded affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at. Some are overflowed with a deluge of teares, for
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169925:26"/> that, which to another hath no ſuch ugly Character ſtampt on it. Opinion is ſufficient to move paſſion, and Opinion many times riſes from the bare ſhewes of things; and yet the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions are no leſſe violent and ſtrong which Opinion retorts on us, then what comes from things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ill. Beautie is a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Ray, which might rayſe our thoughts to the Creator of Lights, who is Beautie it ſelfe; and wherein the Minde might take as much content, with due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on the Giver, as in any other ſparks of that om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent brightneſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169925:26"/> to the Creature. Honour is that badge, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they will honour Vertue: Wealth is a banke againſt the flowings in of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of this life. Yet all theſe befoole our loves, and cheat our affections; they not being brought in by the trials and examinations of Reaſon, but by the ſecret motions and recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Paſſion: for Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, by the Hyperbole and exceſſe of my thoughts, is made another thing to me than it is; being onely thoſe clouds whither the Sunne of mens wit ſend their beames to gild.</p>
               <p>Thus, when wee would
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169925:27"/> immortalize the objects of our Earth-borne wiſhes, or make Earthly Beauties Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; then, by this diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion are our unſatisfied affections betrayed to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, being it muſt be recalled from the height and rate it had carryed the thing too: or if one, in ſtead of true Vertue and Merit, fall in love with vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Breath, and Court that Eccho, being as much taken with thoſe ayrie reverbera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as <hi>Narciſſus</hi> was with the watrie reflection, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for that rich Ore of happineſſe in other mens ſoules, which he would have coyned into reſpect and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169925:27"/> of him; what doth he, but (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayth) poſſeſſe the winde? Or if one admire too much that Idoll of vulgar mindes, Wealth, thinking the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of it conſiſts in the abundance; when as that Divine Aphoriſme delivers, More than what is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the owner hath but to behold it with his eyes. Men augment their joyes from the greatneſſe of their wealth, as they doe their feares from the greatneſſe of the appearance of his dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. All the Ocean ſtrikes a terror in the minde of him like to be drowned, when leſſe than a Tun would ſerve
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169925:28"/> the turne. Or if the whole Ayre, that incompaſſeth the Globe, were infected, one ſhould adde the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the vaſtneſſe of that, to encreaſe his ſorrow, whereas he could ſuck in no more than what conferr'd to his owne mortalitie. Oh, that my wayes were directed with a Line, the Line of thy Word! there being no other Guide out of this intricacie and perplexedneſſe of our owne natures.</p>
               <p>Man was, from the hand of the moſt glorious Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſet on the ſolid <hi>Baſis</hi> of integritie and juſtice, and is now crumbled away into tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, minute-deceits, which
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169925:28"/> hath weakened the ſoliditie of this beſt piece of the Creation. Truth is that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prey mans Soule is in the inqueſt after; and to have it, in ſtead of realities, ſtored onely with maskes and outward formes, it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honours our natures, makes them unhappie and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>The moralitie of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, puts out of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the late Religions of our time: How generous, and how becomming a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy minde, was the advice of that Orator to his friend <hi>Atticus,</hi> then Governour of a Province? Whom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing firſt with the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169925:29"/> and natures of the men he had to deale with, their diſpoſitions, their ends, how farre he might truſt ſome, how farre make uſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; then diſſwades him from Anger, there being nothing more ugly, than to adde bitterneſſe and ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Furie to Power and Command. Afterward, that he be ſure, that in all his carriage he ſhould let the Native ſee, through his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant readineſſe to aid them, and to doe juſtice, he placed his glory in their ſecuritie; and lookt upon their proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie, as the fruits of his prudence, and his good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of their affaires: then,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169925:29"/> ſaith he, will they obey you, with the reſignation of their wills, as to a father. At laſt he concludes, that he ſhould be ſure to let integritie, and juſtice, and wiſdome, be the foundation of his honour and greatneſſe; <hi>haec ſint fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damenta dignitatis tuae:</hi> But now, in ſtead of thoughts inlarged to take care of the publique, their Purſes are onely to take Money in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate. Shall they be able, by the faint rayes of Nature, to copie fairer peeces of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and truer Glory, than this Age, by the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of their ſupernaturall Lights, can afford any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of? Who doth not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169925:30"/> looke upon, with grave re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, theſe Reliques, theſe yet ſtanding Pieces, not winde; which ſhewes, how magnificent a ſtructure man was? Who can but honour the gallantry of the manners of the old <hi>Romans?</hi> Who being called to defend their Countrey, command their Armies, either to oppoſe forraine enemies, or appeaſe domeſtique inſurrections; they deſired onely, that they might have, during their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from home, occaſioned by the Warres, their Plowes and Stocks preſerved, and that they might returne to the pleaſures and contents of their former Countrey
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169925:30"/> lives, indemnified in their eſtates, having diſcharged their obligation to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.</p>
               <p>But how different are the endeavours of men in this age? they being all imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not as in the champion region of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, but in the incloſures of their owne particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. Frugalitie is that Vertue which ſtands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene unpleaſing Taxes, and Gabels, and the peoples hate. Juſtice is like the Sunne in the Spheare of Government, it gives life and light to all: Prudence exerciſe, a Vertue different from the other, not contrary.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:169925:31"/>
               <p>The civill Forts, and Strengths of Kingdomes, are politique Axiomes of Conſervation, drawne out of the bowels of Reaſon, and Experience; which to neglect, were to let goe to ruine thoſe bankes which hindred the invaſion of a ſea of publique calamitie. Thus is that golden Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to which every one did bow, while it was ſupported with Juſtice and Prudence, broke into a numberleſſe companie of inferiour Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies; in ſtead of thoſe great Luminaries, every one goes about with the dim Lights of their little Plots, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the darke corners of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169925:31"/> their private deſignes. So farre, Lord, as we withdraw our ſelves from the Rule and Law thou haſt confined our actions in, ſo farre we leſſen and degenerate; in ſtead of the advancement and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their natures, they debaſe it and becrampe it: there is no progreſſe made, but with all our labour and paines ſhall be found onely to have gone ſo farre on one ſide. Thou art Wiſdome and Righteouſneſſe; in the one, be thou the light of my eyes; in the other, the guide of my life: let me not, Lord, turne aſide to deceit, but looke well to my paths.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:169925:32"/>
               <head>Of Conſtancie and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance.</head>
               <p>COnſtancie is that <hi>Atlas</hi> which upholds mans lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle World; without which, it is but a piece of contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencie, caſuall diſorderly motions, a world of <hi>Atomes.</hi> And yet, Lord, ſuch are the contrary and irregular cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of my life, that I adde to the outward viciſſitudes of the world, the inconſtant motions of my owne breſt. The greater world is full of diverſe and different opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and motions of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet a Coſmicall har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the Vniverſe is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169925:32"/> maintained through all the diverſitie of thoſe workings; and man, while his actions are concentrick, and are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned to the Rule of thoſe ſeverall Lawes God governes us by, he tranſlates the harmonie of Nature to his owne thoughts, they all conſtantly moving in their proper Orbes. I thought I had beene ſo conſolidated within my ſelfe, I could have found none of theſe uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancies; ſo compacted with Precepts and Rules, ſo forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Experience and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, that all ſuch varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions had beene excluded; but, Lord, I perceive my ſelfe all in peeces, involved,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169925:33"/> diſcompoſed: How ſoone are my devouter reſolves made a Trophie to my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate corruptions, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the victories of my more imperious nature? In braverie of Diſcourſe, and fineneſſe of Contemplation, the whole Globe is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time trampled on, the brags of Wealth and Glory deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed; and yet, as if I were not Commander of this ſmall extenſion of Earth, I finde my high-flowne thoughts brought downe to the lure of ſome contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible Vanitie; and that Earth which I even now trod up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, trampling ore my Soule and its affections.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:169925:33"/>
               <p>The Heathens made brave deſcriptions of Vertues; they deſigned and curiouſly decyphered thoſe heavenly Bodies, but knew not one foot of the way into them. Who can but honour their gallant expreſſions? The height and livelineſſe of their contemplations? How magnificent are they in their language, when they with that pomp of rich diſcourſe goe to ſet Reaſon in its Throne, giving it the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and command over the paſſions? And among all the glorious ſtructures of Vertue they have made, with what ſtate and majeſtie doe they leade their Readers to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169925:34"/> that invincible, Fortreſſe of Conſtancie, ſeated on a Rock? Here promiſing, that all the ſtormes of affliction ſhall breake and ruine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on't. The Stoick gravely invites your Hand to goe into his Barke, to ſayle to happineſſe in, ſending Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges to Fortune; aſſuring you, by the prerogative of their Doctrines, a ſhelter from all its ſtormes.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Impavidum ferient ruina.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Who can but admire the heights and tranſcendencies of their Soules? Their Pens well feathered with wit and expreſſion, flying home to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169925:34"/> the mark of moſt mens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, Wealth, Honor, Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and with that <hi>Mercuries</hi> Rod condemning them to the Earth; and againe, a tougher Will, conteſting with Povertie, Diſgrace, Loſſes, diſabling them to make us miſerable. Theſe are the rallyed Forces of mens defeated Reaſons, the recollected ſparks of mans weakened Vnderſtanding, which may yeeld a warmth to our dark and frozen Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And yet for all the vaunts of Philoſophie, our compoſures are looſened; mans Nature got a fall in the Cradle, and in ſtead of a compleat Building, there
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169925:35"/> remaine but the ruines of one.</p>
               <p>Its wiſdome to come out of a ruinous houſe: I deſire, Lord, to come out of my ſelfe, ſelfe-love, ſelfe-confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; let it be my ſtrength, to cleave to thee.</p>
               <p>Error will ſometimes ſeek to get a luſtre to it, from its pretences to this Vertue: How many ſeeme to chide the ſlow progreſſe of their Soule, for not uſing more wings to flye to thoſe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginarie Crownes their delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded zeales were put in hope of? Conſtancie in ſuffering being no infallible ſigne of Truth. Slaves can ſuffer to admiration, and ſome by
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169925:35"/> cuſtome, as <hi>Patiens Lacedae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fix, Lord, this volatile matter, untangle this ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel'd peece of thine, and give me ſuch a conformitie betwixt my practice and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves; ſuch good thoughts, and ſuch a conſtant executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, that in the chain of my life, the latter linke of Grace may joyne to that of Glory; leſt by any inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, or diſcontinuance, breaking ſome one of them, I fall into Torment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:169925:36"/>
               <head>Conſiderations in Travell.</head>
               <p>HE who contents him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe only with as much as he can behold with his eye; the ſtatelineſſe of Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the outward garbe of the People, the rich Liverie Nature hath beſtowed on their Soyle; ſeemes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch a kind of ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, as one ſhould have from getting to be able to reade a different Character, or Letter, without ever ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for the ſenſe or mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contained in them. Out of Natures Alphabet, by the ſeverall poſitions as it
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169925:36"/> were of its Letetrs, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of its outward qualities, all things are thus diverſified in forme and ſhape: but if one would ſtudie intellectuall ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, hee muſt penetrate deeper; conſider the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions of the people, and ſee what influence they have had upon their Lawes, they being framed by Reaſons proportioned to them: to ſee what influence the Lawes have upon the people, in Protection, Wealth, and Peace, for they were framed for the ſureſt defence and procurement of theſe, by the people: to ſee how the tide of their Wealth ebbes or
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169925:37"/> flowes, running in the veines of their Trading; how it may be diverted, how ſtopt: to ſee whether they carry in their owne boſome the ſeeds of their ruine, parties, and faction, and the preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of theſe at Court, and how theſe operate upon their Counſels; how they ſtand in feare or aſſurance of Allyes, or Neighbours, and upon what grounds and intereſts.</p>
               <p>Thus may you view, as it were, the whole frame of Government in motion; a lively repreſentation of it taken from the practick, and not a flouriſhing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of an imaginarie
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169925:37"/> Common-wealth; like a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture drawne only for Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſake, by the obſervation of their ſeverall diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; what they owe to their tempers, their ſeverall fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and mouldings up; what to Diſcipline, and Vertue: one will be better able to get acquaintance of himſelfe, to follow the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Socraticall Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle: to obſerve in the <hi>French</hi> a converſation eaſie and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile, whoſe firſt familiaritie is ſuch, that he hath left himſelfe no power to goe beyond it, overflowing with the prodigall exceſſe of a verball humanitie. On the other ſide of the Hills, a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169925:38"/> people wiſe at home, and converſible abroad; in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves conſiderative, and in converſation agreeable. The Dutch, as if that divine ſpark, his Soule, were drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in its moiſt Lodging, not able to make any depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from himſelfe; not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a carriage ſo fortified with ceremonies, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; not given to Careſſes and Court-like applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but onely ſuch obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, as may make them know hee beleeves none is better than another; their humours fitted and ſiding with equalitie, whereby they have beene eaſier caſt into the mould of a State. In the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169925:38"/> 
                  <hi>French,</hi> what advantages their ſuddenneſſe and firſt violent motions afford, in execution of Commands. The <hi>Dutch</hi> hath his ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe made up, and ayded, by conjunction of Counſels; as if Nature did ſtill incline them to the remedie of their Conſtitutions, by a conſtant communication of their thoughts and delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; their excellencie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like that which hath not its eſteeme from the parts ſimply conſidered, but from the <hi>totum compoſitum.</hi> The <hi>Italians</hi> are fine and quaint in their Counſels, but dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to put in practiſe: what is taken from practiſe,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169925:39"/> is eaſilieſt turned into pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe againe; there being ſo much difference many times betwixt the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things in Bookes, and the things themſelves, as is betwixt a Journey in open day-light, and ſuch a one as <hi>Virgil</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes a wandring by the uncertaine and changing lights of the Moone, in gloomie Woods:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quale ſub incertam Lunam,</l>
                  <l>Est Iter in ſylvis.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:169925:39"/>
               <head>Of Opinions in Religion.</head>
               <p>THe Church hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes beene vext with Opinions; ſome, wittie and ſpeculative; others, groſſe and ugly ones. Religion is called the Myſterie of our Salvation; and yet how converſant is it made in the toyles of wit? <hi>Ingenioſa res eſt, jam eſſe Chriſtianum; Syllogiſmi ſuſtinent Eccleſiam.</hi> Words ſerve to beget Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, wherein great wits, imployed for Victorie, leave the Readers eyes loſt, in that pitch, wherein their high flights had Leſſoned them; they decking Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169925:40"/> up with the feathers of humane Learning, to be able to ſoare in the ſubtill ayre of Controverſie.</p>
               <p>When Ambition or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit hath turned the edge of an Heretikes wit on one ſide, to maintaine an Hereſie; how ingeniouſly doth hee wander in the ſhades of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie? uncharitably wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Texts of Scripture, diligently weeding the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, making up a ſolid Body of a Diſcourſe, well-ſpirited with wit and inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; where is hard nicetie, elaborate thinneſſe, weake fineneſſe. Theſe are curious Models, which conforme not to the Prototype, but
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169925:40"/> are delicate contextures of the Arts of Reaſoning. They needed not to have retrived an old Opinion of a new world, ſince they might have found a new world of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, fill'd with the ayre of Fancie, ſurrounded with the Ocean of Error. As in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, by their new Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, they have made, as it were, ſpurious and falſe Globes; that even that ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Genius</hi> of <hi>Ovid</hi> comes neerer the truth of the Worlds Creation, than ſome of their chiefe Dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in the Schooles: So in Divinitie, which ſhould be the pure white innocent Queen of our Soules, breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169925:41"/> upon them the ſoft and gentle gales of Joy, Peace, and Love; now they have made her like a <hi>Scylla,</hi> girt about with barking Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, full of lowd and liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Queſtions and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes. They have drawne (as it were) upon the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Body of Theologie falſe and ſuppoſed Lines; new motions, fabulous and imaginarie: yet though it be beautifull in its native Dreſſe, and needes not the advantage of any forraine Luſter, yet it diſdaines not to be attended on by its pure and intellectuall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant Learning; many times explaining it ſelfe in its
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169925:41"/> notions, and uſing its helpe for Confutation, Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Explanation. There are deepe Abyſmes contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in its moſt familiar ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, which are but the condiſcentions and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as it were, to our capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities: there is a profound ſimplicitie in its plaineſt poſitions; and that ſentence, <hi>Whom God loves he chaſtiſeth,</hi> makes miſerie it ſelfe Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricall. If it be too fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar with artificiall diſcuſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in a few diſcents, or Genealogies of Arguments, it forgets its heavenly birth, and begets affinitie with Reaſon. All Arguments move upon the formes of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169925:42"/> ſpeech, Syllogiſme, they are the Products of Reaſon; and by a ſucceſſion of Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Concluſion at laſt being become ſo farre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from that which ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally begot them, that it many times hath not onely loſt the ſimilitude of favour, but hath altered its inward nature.</p>
               <p>Some late Philoſophers have proved, that Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmes are not ſufficient to evince Phyſicall Verities, but that the ſubtilties even of Natures workings evade it ſubtill formes; how much more Sacred Divinitie, which lyes not levell with Reaſon? It being no more
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169925:42"/> able to fathome or reach its tranſcendencies and ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, then a little thred can by the arme of man be throwne about the heavenly Pole; ſeeing it can be proved by Reaſon, that Religion is above it, and to be left to mens beleefes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boetius</hi> ſaith excellently well, That Reaſon, to ſee the truth of thoſe things, muſt goe out of it ſelfe; and that the minde ſhould be lifted up to the height of that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme intelligence, which ſhould there behold what in it ſelfe it cannot; that is, how certain and determinate previſion may go before the uncertaine events of things.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169925:43"/> He who is the Truth, and the Light, though not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by the darkneſſe of the World, converſt with men on Earth in the depth of humilitie, in the exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of obedience, in the conſtant practice of each holy Vertue. There is a pure and heavenly Light annext to the devout aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the Soule; for the blind eye of the minde doth not know how to looke up to the God of glory, if hee from above ſhine not upon it with the inward beames of his Grace: and though Light deſcends from above, from the Father of Lights, yet a holy innocence, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169925:43"/> true humilitie, ſends clearer Lights of Knowledge up to the braine, than any ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations can ſend downe the warmth of Charitie to the heart: for the Sonne of God (the Light it ſelfe) deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, covered as it were with humilitie, and the heart is the ſeat of it; and ſo that inacceſſible Light is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to us, in the darke coverings and habits of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliations. One may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the braine with loftie and ayrie Contemplations, and yet let his Soule ſlip away, for want of Charitie, which is the Soule of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; by the infuſion of which we are animated, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169925:44"/> ſpiritually live. Religion is a practicall Syllogiſme, whoſe premiſſes goe for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if there be not the active concluſion of well-doing.</p>
               <p>Therefore, Lord, while others cannot agree, in what order to range and ranke good workes, and Faith; let it be my Faith, that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thy will is neceſſarie; and thy will is, our holineſſe, and the practice of good workes; and make it part of my workes, to pray for Faith and the encreaſe of it. Grant, Lord, that while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers cannot agree about the manner of thy Comming, that my heart may be ſo
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169925:44"/> taken up with the Faith and joy of thy beloved preſence, that it give not my head leyſure curiouſly to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the manner of it.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the ſweet Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſures, the bleſſed Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliations, when the diſputes of good things are ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in the heavenly frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; executions of them; in this calme Harbour doth the Veſſell of a Soule, toſt with the windes of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, ſafely reſide.</p>
               <p>And now, Lord, the Ship of thy Church, toſt amidſt the furious waves of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, ſeemes to ſtand in danger of Ruine: but we know, the Gates of Hell
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169925:45"/> have all their powers here defeated, though we crie in the tenderneſſe of our paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; <hi>Master, careſt thou not that we periſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not ſo eaſie to give a Reaſon of ſome Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in the Church, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in ones Studie, as to goe abroad, and ſee that great fabrick of Power, and the vaſt Treaſures, which are built upon the foundation of this nice Schoole-Divinitie: if the Church ſeeme to ſeeke in ſome Doctrines, its but oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned, as the Fever of that ſick man in <hi>Martial</hi> was, who was onely ſick, to take occaſion to ſhew the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169925:45"/> of his houſe-hold-ſtuffe:</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Faciunt hanc ſtragula febrim.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Error is many times more magnificent in its ſtructures than Truth; yet, as its Gates, perhaps, may be more gilded, and ſhine more gawdily, yet they are like that Doore of Sleepe in <hi>Virgil;</hi> the fine one being that which let out all the falſe Dreames, while Truth had its paſſage out of thoſe that were plainer.</p>
               <p>Reformation in Religion is like diſtill'd waters, which being too much endevoured to be heightned, being once
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169925:46"/> at their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they relapſe and loſe of their ſpirit and force; and mens ſpirits not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where they have deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that Centre and point of Truth, which ſhould have fixt them, ſtagger and reele in the circumference and round of their owne fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
               <p>Religion fires mens hearts with holy zeale, making them mourne, as it were, in the diſſolutions and aſhes of their paſt ſinnes; but its no incendiarie, to delight in thoſe of Townes and Cities. Religion proclaimes a holy Warre againſt Sinne, and Vice, but never blowes the Trumpet of Sedition. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169925:46"/> exacts from its ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hearts, homage to the King of Power, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes all earthly Crowns; <hi>My Kingdome</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is not of this world.</hi> Religion hath its power, and force, to the deſtruction of its e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; but he hath ſaid, it ſhould be with the word of his mouth, and that the wrath of man fulfils not the juſtice of God. Religion is like the Sunne, it gives light and life to all, while it keeps its owne heavenly courſe; but being made to incline to earthly ends, it cauſes a conflagration. What ever good effects are produced from any falſe or erronious
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169925:47"/> Religions, its by vertue of thoſe Opinions and Tenets mixt with it, that beare a conformitie to Truth; and what ill actions ſeeme to flow, or be occaſioned from the true Religion, they are the effects of thoſe errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Opinions, that they have mingled with their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie, and beare a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the malignitie of mans nature, rather than the others paritie.</p>
               <p>Let me not ſeeke, Lord, thy living Word among the dead acts of naturall Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, neither in the Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of unruly Zeales, nor from among the Glories, Wealth, and Ends men have
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169925:47"/> on Religion; but let my Soule ſuck from the breſts of my Mother, Truth and Salvation, thy Church converting thy Word to my foode, and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <head>Of enjoyment of Pleaſure.</head>
               <p>MUſick ſounds beſt to one in the darke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no other outward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject diſtracts his attention: and to heare the Muſick of thoſe Precepts delivered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Pleaſure, one muſt ſhut up from his eye the delightfull objects of the ſenſe; which other wayes
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169925:48"/> would (perhaps) ſteale away his thought. Yet this is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a remedie fitted for the weakneſſe of the eye, which ſo readily recommends to the minde the flattering Courtſhips of theſe Curti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zans of the Senſe. But to fortifie and ſtrengthen the minde againſt them, its bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to view them all in the light, looking upon them with the eye of Reaſon; and there, all their falſe ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours would not ſhew ſo brave. Hee who hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſt with them moſt freely, hath ſooneſt found, that their inward diſpoſitions, and qualities, give not him leave to live ſo happily in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169925:48"/> their enjoyment, as their outward beautie flattered him with the hopes of: he hath ſooneſt pierc'd through that thin and pleaſing rinde wherewith they are covered, and taſtes of them as they be, in their owne natures; where hee findes anxietie, unſatisfied melancholy, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, decay of fortune. But to let alone thoſe ingenious invectives and ſtoicall ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings againſt Pleaſure, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending them to a common place; one may obſerve of it, that moſt men love to be wiſe by their owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Mans nature is ſo poore and indigent a thing of it ſelfe, that it turnes it
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169925:49"/> ſelfe every where to ſeeke ſatisfaction; and its the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Nature, delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to draw us to perform its actions: ſhe hath annext a Pleaſure to the uſe of our ſenſes, that otherwiſe it would be a troubleſome thing to maintain our lives; that great Bleſſing of, <hi>Goe and multiplie,</hi> ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending of it. Pleaſure may make its ſoft impreſſions upon our yeelding ſenſe, and its to put off our <hi>ſpecies,</hi> to be inſenſible of them. Some would make man another thing than he is, by robbing him of his affections; Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, ſay they, would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him into ſtrange and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169925:49"/> foraine ſhapes; and ſome of the Philoſophers, for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, would convert him into a ſtone; as if he muſt endure the tranſmutations of the Poet, and act his <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſharpe and fineſt ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Pleaſure ſide with Vertue, and Temperance; while they periſh upon the ruines of their ſatiated and plenarie fruitions; and as long as they make no greater ſound in the curious inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of man than ſuits with the harmonie of his ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer motions, they helpe the Muſick: but if their greater noyſe drowne the voyce of Reaſon, or the higher facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169925:50"/> of the Soule, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come lovers of Pleaſures, more than lovers of God.</p>
               <p>Let all thy bleſſings, Lord, thy Methods, and Workes, make ſtayres for my Soule, to aſcend to thy right hand, <hi>where are Pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <head>A Contemplation on our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours hanging on the Croſſe.</head>
               <p>NOw am I freed from the noyſe of Paſſions, whilſt with one looke they are ſtruck dumbe. Now am I delivered from the Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of inſulting affections, whilſt in him crucified they
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169925:50"/> behold their owne death. The glories and pompe of the world have loſt their pretences, whilſt the Sonne of Glory and Power ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, cloathed with the fraile garment of humane nature, In this bleſſed ſhade, no poyſonous Vice will live; the Serpent of Pride will not endure the looke of the true Brazen Serpent, to ſee him humbled to the death of the Croſſe; Envie flyes hence, to ſee him ſuffer for his enemies.</p>
               <p>And now not left to, but freed from my ſelfe, my frozen and congealed heart begins to melt and thaw, diſſolving into teares, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169925:51"/> for its ſinnes, for which I ſee my Saviours heart to bleed. Here I ſit, and bathe the wings of my Soule (my affections) in the flames of Gods holy love; and whilſt the fire burnes below in my heart, my eyes boyle over above with fervent ſtreames: here, in devout extaſies, my Soule loſes it ſelfe, in thoſe raviſhments of divine love: I goe out of my ſelfe, in wonderment, not able to comprehend it; but joyfully throw my ſelfe into thoſe depths, deſiring to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by it. The joyes of a Soule divinely in love, border upon thoſe inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible ones above; for
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169925:51"/> they ſwallow one up, in their profound immenſities, and leave no capacitie for Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to marſhall them up, in words and expreſſions; the Wards, as it were, of that Key being no way fitted, to open the Lock of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of this Love; but leaves mens Soules holily inebriated and over-flowed with the deluge of Pleaſures and Joyes; I becomming rather theirs, than they mine, being turned all to Joy and Love.</p>
               <p>And now my Soule being melted with the meditation of thy Paſſion, let it be pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out to thee in Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; let the beames of thy
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169925:52"/> owne tranſcendent Love be reflected back againe from my heart, upon the face of others; that thus ſhining one to another, and all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving our Lights from thee, may at laſt be fixt in thy owne Court, for ever ſill'd with the beames of the joy of thy preſence.</p>
               <p>Let others ſit in the Chaire of ſubtill Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, while I ſit at the feet of my Saviour, in meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Paſſion: Let o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers boaſt of their falſe Retreats, their Groves, and <hi>Eliziums;</hi> while under the ſhades of thy ſharpe and thornie Crowne my Soule rejoyces; nay, while in thoſe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169925:52"/> ſhades which Croſſes and Afflictions ſhall caſt upon my life, in conformitie to my Saviours ſuffering, my Soule rejoyces.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <head>A Contemplation upon a retyred life.</head>
               <p>THe Poets ſometimes gratifie the largeneſſe of mans Soule with their loftie flights, writing to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie; and in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of their fancie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with Deities, tumbling among the Starres with <hi>Iove:</hi> and anon, let the motions of their Spirits downe againe, to view the contents of moderate and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169925:53"/> private fortunes. Thus wee ſee ſometime the Sceane of the greateſt mens lives al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; now repreſenting you the proſpect of Armies, Triumphs of Victories, Grandeur of State, the glory of Courts, Camps, and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; anon, in their roomes, ſucceeding Groves and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Rivers private Walks, Diſcourſes of the Worlds Vanities, Experiments of Nature, and ſuch Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of ſolitarineſſe: When all the ſwellings of Pride and vain Opinions are falne, and Nature freed from thoſe affectations it hath got a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, it acknowledgeth it ſelfe, its owne Bents and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169925:53"/> inclinations. A life led ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Nature, is the reall enjoying of things themſelves: but if accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Art and Opinion, its like as in Pictures; they view things drawne well to the Life, repreſentations of Love, Honour, and Vertue; yet nothing but Colours, that loſe their glories by mens neerer approaches. The joyes of an active life are more agreeable to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, moving in the Sphere of Vertue, than any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions from ſocietie can afford, whoſe privilege can onely be, to thinke Vertue. The maſculine power of the minde is not beholding to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169925:54"/> places for their ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but what is the true and reall dignitie of one place before another, by an intellectuall Chymiſtrie he can extract, and tranſlate to his owne minde their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminencies. There can in no place be wanting Groves, Rivers, ſinging of Birds; our bodies are a ſhadie Grove, where our Soules ſit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templating; the Muſick of the Birds without, are all Gods creatures, which, as it were, in ſo many diverſified Notes doe ſweetly ſing their Makers prayſe; the Rivers, are that flux wherein all humane things are, Times, Perſons, Things, which by a
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169925:54"/> ſucceſſion of their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible and alterable parts, doe ſtill keepe up that current. Theſe thoughts are, as it were, the better <hi>Genius,</hi> which attends the Lakes: without which, their retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are but the refuges of mens ſickly humours; where they begin to live of their maladie, rather than to cure it; and doe onely ſacrifice the fumes of melancholy, for that incenſe of ſervice, which they owe as a tribute for their being.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that would make loaneneſſe acceptable, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing men, as through a Proſpective, to behold the greatneſſe of Structures, and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169925:55"/> braverie of Courts, through the humilitie of a Cottage, doe make ones deluded fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie the ground of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, imagining that he ſtill enjoyes thoſe things, which commonly ſo ſwells mens mindes, that they cannot with that evenneſſe of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment taſte thoſe purer plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, which ariſe from the obſervation of Nature, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as it were his Diſeaſe his Cure; the immoderate eſteeme of the other having ſo vitiated his pallat, that he can relliſh nothing elſe, though it be by the proxie of the fancie.</p>
               <p>Lord, give mee <hi>Iacobs</hi> Dreames, that my very
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:169925:55"/> imaginations may repreſent things as Ladders, whereon I may ſee thy Goodneſſe, Wiſdome, and Power deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending, our <hi>Allelujahs</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <head>Conſiderations on theſe Times.</head>
               <p>ALL this goodly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick is broke up,<note place="margin">The miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes of a Civill Warre.</note> and disbanded; the Elements of it rudely blended, and hurld together: that which was high, becomming low; and that which was low, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming high. The towring Eagle is ſhot by an Arrow made of the ſame Tree, where he had built his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169925:56"/> Neſt; and in that Red Sea of Bloud, with which Pride and Faction hath overflowed this Iſland, is the Sunne of Juſtice and Religion almoſt ſet: men growing onely politick in Ruine, and wittie in Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the beſt meanes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the worſt ends; the vigour and ſtrength of the Commonwealth conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on a Diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>A Civill Warre once but named, what evills throng not into our conquered ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations? How doth our unhappie Country feaſt the eyes of their enemies with the numerous funeralls of its owne Children? What
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:169925:56"/> cruell Opinions are enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, reſiding as Tygers in the breſts of men, to which muſt be offred the Victimes and Sacrifices of their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Countreymen? What monſters of new Faiths lodge in their breſts, that thus devoure and prey up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tender Virgins, I meane the ancient integritie and candor of their diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? How doe they dabble in one anothers bloud? ſearching one anothers bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, as if like poyſonous Scorpions they ſhould be bruiſed, to yeeld an oyle to cure the poyſon given by their owne ſtings.<note place="margin">Of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Warre</note>
               </p>
               <p>A forraine Warre is like
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169925:57"/> Lightnings in the Skie, which purifies and cleanſes thoſe upper Regions; but then Nature keepes its ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: whereas if the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments themſelves, of which this World conſiſts, ſhould make a Warre together, that muſt needs bring a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. If men ſaw no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it, its enjoyned their beliefes, <hi>That a Houſe divided cannot ſtand.</hi> Oh miſerable Triumph of our Ruine! Oh wofull Pompe of our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction! How all things weare the Liverie of Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning! There may you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne Juſtice in its ſable Weedes, ſo farre gone in Melancholy, ſcarce ever to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169925:57"/> be ſeene abroad; here Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in a corner weeping, grieved to ſee, that they have ſo long, like Whifflers, kept the Doore of the Church againſt the comming in of ſtrangers, till all the Church is become full of ſtrange Opinions; and that they never more take care to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare honeſt and good men, than when moſt eſpecially they intend to deceive: in another place, the Lawes wildly running about, and lamenting, yet ſo lowd, that all take notice of it.</p>
               <p>And now, as in <hi>Orpheus</hi> Theatre, upon the ceaſing of this Muſick of the Laws, men returne to their fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zies
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169925:58"/> and factions;<note place="margin">Men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult not with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but with par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> they doe not debate, examine, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, but follow, adhere, and combine: <hi>Sequere poſt me,</hi> is the Motto of the Times; every one taking notice of the Signe, where he hath taken up his Lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging; ranging themſelves in ſeverall Boxes, which beare ſome outward Badge of the Faction. The peoples minds with the fire of Zeale, and the heat of theſe Troubles, being become fluid, and melted, are caſt in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Moulds that wittie Contrivers had faſhioned: The vulgar ſpirits, which make up the multitude, to preſerve their beloved
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:169925:58"/> Chattels, are prepared to ſide with parties, ſince that begets ſupport and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; and that he ſhould be a prey to both, without being a partie to one. Thus every thing is imbraced, to which Ambition, armed with Power, can make its way: <hi>Quiſque deliberat de partibus, de ſumma nemo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The wiſdome of later times conſiſted in wittie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions of theſe Troubles;<note place="margin">The wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of later times to divert troubles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaith <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con.</hi>
                  </note> whereby the many evills threatning the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth were clearely ſhun'd. An example whereof, wee finde in former times, in the people of <hi>Capua;</hi> who being reſolved to have their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:169925:59"/> no longer to rule over them, one who being well thought of by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and intending to oblige the Senatours, uſed thus his power he had with them: he tells the Senatours, if they would follow his advice, he would ſave them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they conſented all to be lockt up in a roome, and thither he brings the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, pretending he had got them into that poſture, to ſacrifice them all to their furies (for the people will ever be deceived:) but he deſired of them, before they proceeded to execution, they would chuſe from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, who
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169925:59"/> ſhould have the others pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: They, divided by their particular affections, and ſeverall judgements, were brought to put in practice the puniſhment they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the others, upon themſelves; falling into ſo great difference and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: To prevent which, they all cry'd, to have the former Senatours releaſed, and reſtored.</p>
               <p>Though the care of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times did keepe this humour low, yet,<note place="margin">The miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of this, to buckle with them</note> like ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſinne, it was alwayes ſprouting into action.</p>
               <p>If in the naturall body any malignant humour be predominant, it preſently
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169925:60"/> confounds that harmonie of health, which conſiſts in an equall and juſt temperature of the humours: ſo in the civill Body, if thoſe that are lovers of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth grow inferiour in number to thoſe affecting change, its like the health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full temperature diſordered by a prevailing noxious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: its the miſerie of theſe preſent times, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with this obſtinate Maſſe of the matter. What evills happen through the remedie, is like ſickneſſe occaſioned by Phyſick; and yet many times Potions are entertained with worſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces than a Conſumption<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:169925:60"/> And ſuch is the nature of ſome Sickneſſe, to flatter the partie into the opinion, that it is his onely delight; and ſo ſubtilly mingles it ſelfe with their blouds, that the other purple ſtreames of Nature ſeeme to uſurpe their azure channels.</p>
               <p>There be in all things circumſtances, and outward accidents, which mock the Polititians Counſels, which are governed by the higheſt Providence, and, like the Kingdome of Heaven, comes not by obſervation; yet here we may view the parties up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stage, and ſee how the Sceane is layd.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Presbyterian</hi> ſhewes
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:169925:61"/> you out of the Word, a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church, which is Chriſts own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which ought to be ſuperiour to all other Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Juriſdictions; and ſaith, its lawfull by Armes to impoſe it upon the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, in caſe he refuſe: his practice hath ſeconded his Opinion.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Independent</hi> growes angry at it, that any reſtraint of the Spirit ſhould be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and ſaith, its libertie of Conſcience, hee can prove it out of the Bible: its that he hath fought for, and will have.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cavalier</hi> admoniſhes every man to returne to the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169925:61"/> obedience of the King, and the Lawes made by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the free people of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A fourth cryes out,<note place="margin">Forainers fore-ſaw this, and helpt to caſt in theſe ſeeds and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, upon which they contrived our ruine.</note> they are all Heretikes; and theſe Diviſions are Judgements light upon them, for depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from their Mother-Church.</p>
               <p>The Matter being thus prepared, the Spark would eaſily be procured: And thus are our men placed juſt in that poſture, our enemies deſire to play their Game in.</p>
               <p>Our wittie Adverſaries, by a penetrating inſight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the conſtitution of this State, have long ſince con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:169925:62"/> our Ruine upon thoſe very Principles this Warre hath begun upon, and may be continued: Thoſe inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious artificers of our Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, dexterouſly applying their active to paſſives; and by electing fit inſtruments, aptly working upon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall parties, have contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our diſſolution. Though other peccant humours have flowed in, and the ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practiſes of great ones yeelded their malignant aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects, yet the grand matter of the Diſeaſe lay within: and that ſharpe humour in the Body of the Kingdome being ſet on fire, hath turned it into a Feaver.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:169925:62"/>
               <p>They knew well the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of our Countrey, (which is now made too ſanguine) as appeares by that Draught of our Ruine, delineated by the Pen of <hi>Campanella;</hi> who, though ſhut up in his Cloyſter, had inlarged his minde to the conſideration of all Crownes: And writing to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> how he might ſo treat with every Kingdome and Republique, that taking hold of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves afforded, he might become Monarch of the Weſt part of the World: And concerning the affaires of theſe Iſlands, he adviſeth
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:169925:63"/> thus: That the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſhould ſend to King <hi>Iames</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to promiſe him his aſſiſtance to the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> in caſe of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions; and to get back from him ingagements, for the advancement of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion; or at leaſt not to diſturbe his Plate-Fleet by Sea, wherein their Shipping (ſaith he) is ſo powerfull: and at the ſame time to ſend his Emiſſaries abroad, which ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh in the people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> mindes the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the former ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities betwixt the two Nations; and to ſharpen and ſowre the mindes of the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:169925:63"/> Nobilitie, to inſinuate to them, That the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into <hi>England,</hi> would beſtow his Places, Honours, and Preferments, upon his Countreymen, to their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-valuing and diſ-reſpect; as alſo in Parliament, that it be aſſured the Biſhops, if the King were admitted once into <hi>England,</hi> he would bring along with him the <hi>Presbyterie</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to their deſtruction: Then by wittie <hi>Florentines,</hi> on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe maintained at <hi>Bruxels,</hi> to negotiate here with the moſt eminent of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie that were Catholikes, promiſing each of them a part (the one not knowing
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:169925:64"/> of his negotiation to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) that they ſhould be the Heads of his partie, in the Diviſions which would hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen among them.</p>
               <p>Thus, ſaith the wittie Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick, you ſhall ſowe the feeds of an immortall War among them; that by their continuall Diſtractions, they will not be able to hinder you, in your Deſignes upon others: or at laſt, the parties growne deſperate in Armes, ſhall divide the Kingdome into little Principalities, whereby at laſt they will turne your prey.</p>
               <p>Thus doe they enjoy all our heats and Calentures, and at thoſe fires which are
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169925:64"/> given in our Warres, bring to maturitie their Deſigne of our Ruine; while each partie ſeekes to ſupport it ſelfe with Counſells, and Strength, ſeparated from that of the publique.</p>
               <p>Is there leſſe danger,<note place="margin">The fruits of theſe Warres no other than they deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> if this be practiſed by a neerer State? Perhaps, with the ingredients of many more fine and well-layed Plots. The Moone hath greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon the Earth than the other Planets; not by reaſon of its magnitude, as vicinitie. Let them bee phlegmatick, and have no Deſigne; ſtupid, and have no braine; (and can wee thinke ſo of them, whoſe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169925:65"/> malice is as active as their conſtitution?) yet we force upon them the enjoyment of their Ambitions; they ſuffer our heats to tyre us.</p>
               <p>What is the fruit of all the Bloud, and Treaſure, which the full Purſes, and the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton veines of <hi>England</hi> have laviſhed out? Doth not the preſent poſture of things repreſent us in ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as they fore-ſaw wee ſhould fall in? The King in Priſon, the Church in Schiſme, the Countrey in Oppreſſion, the Citie in Faction: new armed men dayly ſpringing up from thoſe Dragons teeth, which are ſo artificially ſowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:169925:65"/> us. They doe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the nimble daſhes of their Pen, ſeeke to deface as it were, with one blot, all the faire and flouriſhing Letter of this Government, but with Armes doe lay in duſt what bravely rear'd his head with glory to the Skie. Doe they not meditate of Cantonizing? And to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the ſame Power they have pull'd down, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it by the ſame Armes with which they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the other. Is not that faire and goodly Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, which uſed to repreſent the beautifull image of the Common-wealth, broke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeverall pieces, each of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169925:66"/> which repreſent ſeverall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Is not that Mould wherein our Lawes were caſt, uſed onely now for to have inſtruments of Warre fore-caſt in? Doth not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day the Caſe grow more perplext and intricate? New knots, which the moſt cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hand will be never able dextrouſly to undoe, except they be cut; and the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Sword muſt dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon us our former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries. Is it not truly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that Armes once rayſed, turne to many uſes, which at firſt were never thought of?</p>
               <p>And thus our miſerie, like <hi>Proteus,</hi> begets every day
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:169925:66"/> new formes and ſhapes. The farther wee ſend our eyes, to looke what will become of theſe Diviſions; doe wee not loſe them in thoſe vaſt depths of Miſerie and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, in that Gulfe of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, wee doe precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate our ſelves into? Is not the fire onely likely to be quenched with the Ruines of the Houſe?</p>
               <p>One may ſeeke <hi>England</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and not finde it,<note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſht.</note> as touching its Lawes and Conſtitutions; the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being like a Ship that is almoſt covered with bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, ſcarce viſible, yet in being, the outward adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious condition of the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:169925:67"/> thing onely altered: And whether it ſhall be brought into the Port of Peace, or it muſt finde in thoſe vaſt gapings and yawnings of the Sea, a liquid Grave; Heaven only is the Inſuring Office.</p>
               <p>The people doe not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the Reaſon, and Wiſdome of thoſe Lawes, by the benefit whereof, they had their lives and eſtates ſecured; till by the neglect of them, the effects thereof fall upon them, in Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Injuries, and Wrongs; and till, in the utter extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of Miſerie, they learn the cauſes of mens entring firſt into Societie.</p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:169925:67"/>
               <p>If men make uſe of their prerogative, and that part wherein men excell their fellow Creatures, they will finde there is no way imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to hinder the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a State, but by the reducement of it to its prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; for every State, drawne within its proper Rules and Lawes, is ſtrong, like the Tortoyſe, within its ſelfe: but if through abuſe, in time, they wander out of themſelves, into other pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, they become weake and obnoxious.</p>
               <p>A State founded upon Principles, proportioned and fitted for a Warre, finds it ſelfe unſupported in a
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169925:68"/> Peace; and when that which was the ground of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers upholding, is taken away, it of it ſelfe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes.</p>
               <p>Its a viſuall deluſion, to thinke the Land goes from us, when we put off from the Land; the Shoare hath not left the Boat, but the Boat the Shoare: the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is founded in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, in the perſon of the King the ſupreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:169925:68"/>
               <head>Of Bookes and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</head>
               <p>THe Cabinet wherein the Pearle of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is contained, receives ornament and augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the Pearle it ſelfe no inlargement, or advantage, but in the beautie is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on its outward caſe. Words and expreſſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh Knowledge to us, and the various compoundings of mens Conceits are infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and men are glorious and ſplendid in the Arts of Speech: but as words are multiplyed by the diverſe ſetting and joyning of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:169925:69"/> ſo are Bookes growne numerous by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and different delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the things under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in Nature; that one may juſtly reſume that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Complaint, That Bookes are encreaſed, but not Learning. The account of mens Travels into the remoteſt parts of Arts and Sciences, are exact and full; and for every one who have only by a <hi>Compendium</hi> view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Confines of ſome of them, to write a Relation of his Journey, is to fill the world with imperfect <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of their <hi>junior</hi> ſallyes and excurſions: and if hee would avoid running upon
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:169925:69"/> things alreadie performed, and gaine a glory, <hi>Quâ ſe quoque poſsit tollere humo,</hi> he muſt venture for a new Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverie, by which the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of the intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all world may be truly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged. The moſt obſerving eye will hardly bring any thing from our neighbour Countries, <hi>Spaine,</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> which hath eſcaped the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious ſcrutinies of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Travellers; but thoſe who flye over the flowrie fields of Learning, upon the wing of ſublimer inquiries, and returne well laden with the <hi>Nectar</hi> of true Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and Science, to the Hives of Learning, make
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:169925:70"/> their Profeſſions as much beholding to them, as they are to their Profeſſions; live nobly of their own Labours; not like Drones, idly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing ſtill with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances of others. Error now covers the Preſſe with its ſable wings, and uſeth that priviledge onely to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large its commerce with the world, being inabled with more celeritie to hold a ſpeedier intelligence with the ſoules of men: ſuch a ſwarm of miſ-ſhapen Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets flying every where, up and downe, like Batts, that loves the Night; which, upon the returne of the Sunne, become condemned
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:169925:70"/> to ccrners: And grant, Lord, that the Sunne of Majeſtie, which thou haſt ſet in the Spheare of our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by his ſudden appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againe in our Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon; thoſe Birds of the Night, unto whoſe eyes thoſe Royall Beames are mortall, may goe to thoſe places whereto Darkneſſe is baniſhed.</p>
               <p>The Schooles ſwell, as if they had reacht the higheſt Linke of Knowledge; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the opinion of thoſe, who thought that they were all placed above their too modeſt Reaſons, and that nothing was to bee knowne. Some nobler wits
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169925:71"/> have with the armes of their reaſon extended the Empire and command of mans un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding over Nature, beyond the limits of any extant Authors, uſing the Motto of that great Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <hi>Plus ultra;</hi> while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have beene readie to apply to theſe, as ſome did to the martiall expeditions of the other beyond <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi> Pillars, preſenting a Crab, with the Motto of <hi>Plus citrà.</hi> Certainely, true Science is a ſolid thing, and carries one rather to the bottome &amp; depth of things, than lifts one up in ayrie eſtimations, like that falſe Knowledge mentioned by
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:169925:71"/> Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> accompanied with that flatuous qualitie: Therefore, a little to lay downe their Plumes, and lay aſide the ſwelling opinions of the compleat and full en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of the meanes of Knowledge, without provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Academick rage, they may caſt their eye, what eſteeme one of their moſt Learned had of their auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarie &amp; inſtrumentall Arts, in one of their Methods he takes,<note place="margin">Hooker,</note> That it will keep men from growing over-wiſe; and that how-ever this Age carries the name of a Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Age, yet if men had the right helpe and aide of Arts added to their reaſons,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:169925:72"/> wherewith their inquiries might be advantaged, they ſhould as farre goe beyond the learnedſt man now, as the learnedſt man now doth a child. One was handſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commended for his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with the Lawes and Methods of Nature, while others loſt themſelves in a wilderneſſe of notions, and art of Methods:
<q>
                     <l>Reliqui cum Vlyſſe promundum vagantur,</l>
                     <l>Tu cum Penelope domi moranis.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Underſtanding is like a Looking-Glaſſe, which repreſents the images of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:169925:72"/> things ſet before it: The wayes and Arts of Empire and Governments preſented there, Creates the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall pictures of thoſe things, which begets that Science which is called <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities:</hi> and when by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of mans Minde, which can looke into it ſelfe, and ſee its ſelfe, all its paſſions, affections, and how theſe command each other, and how Reaſon, them; then are the internall images of thoſe things repreſented in that Chryſtalline Glaſſe: which notions conſtitute that Science, named <hi>Ethicks;</hi> man, as it were by a reflexed beame of Reaſon, made viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:169925:73"/> to himſelfe. When the Proſpect is altered, and the motions and courſe of the Heavens are contemplated; the Lawes of Nature impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon thoſe heavenly Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies being underſtood, frames there that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Aſtronomie:</hi> and when the Minde deſcends and viewes the lower Globe, there doth the deſcription of the lower Globe lively made, in the underſtanding, become that Science of <hi>Geographie.</hi> Truer know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is acquired, by the inſpection into the Booke of Nature, and the things themſelves, than by the things themſelves, or the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:169925:73"/> Booke of Nature, can be knowne, by looking onely into the underſtanding; for the truth of thoſe things are without: the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are truth, which being underſtood, become ſo too in the underſtanding. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many are ingenious, in giving reaſons of Natures workings, framed onely by their active fancies, and preſcribe other imagined wayes and Lawes, than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Nature is governed by; who doe, as it were, in ſtead of relating a true Hiſtorie, make a <hi>Romance,</hi> and tell the adventures of ſome fabulous <hi>Hero:</hi> it belonging to the Poets, to mold the World
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:169925:74"/> over againe by fiction; to the Philoſopher, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the true World.</p>
               <p>All Learning, is but Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and it, applyed to the Conſideration of ſeverall things, beget ſeveral Names: as the Sea ſaluting the coaſts of <hi>Spaine,</hi> is called the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Sea; and leaving that for <hi>Ireland,</hi> begets the name of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Sea: though men have beene ſo deſirous, for oſtentation of Art, to ſet out each part and portion of Knowledge ſo admirable, for curioſitie of method, and tearmes, that it almoſt (by the circumſcription of the Rules ſet about it) hath forgot its affinitie with the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:169925:74"/> reſt. Knowledge got from the things rhemſelves, doe ſettle the Minde in the true value and eſteeme of every thing; but that which is got-from Man himſelfe, and ſo many Bookes, by a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion they beare with the things, doe benight the Underſtanding, and fill the Minde with miſtaken paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: The attaining ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in Knowledge, and Learning, puts men in the ſame condition, as if they had ſeene no farther then the third or fourth dayes worke of the Creation; whereas he that attaines more, ſtill is preſented to him what is more glorious, and ſaw not
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:169925:75"/> before; till in the end he attaine the full view of the <hi>Oeconomie</hi> of this great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, and make the true uſe of Gods works, by admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his infinite Power, and Goodneſſe; reſting on which, is the Soules true Sabbath.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <head>Of the viciſsitude of Things.</head>
               <p>IT is obſerved by a late Philoſopher, that there be certaine Idols begot in the mindes of men; ſome, ariſing out of their owne individuall tempers; others, out of the imperfections of our common nature: whence
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:169925:75"/> many (ſaith he) conceit to themſelves a more perfect circular method in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Heavens, than indeed the nature of thoſe Bodies will admit; man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apt to imagine all things after an exact order, concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved within himſelfe. Thus doe they erre againſt the Changes and Revolutions, with which all things la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, who fancie a more conſtant proceſſe of things than is ſutable to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering diſpoſition of all things. The elements are in continuall tranſmigration, and alternative converſions; their qualities forme our conſtitutions, and our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:169925:76"/> which have affinitie with their fellow creatures, act upon our mindes; that inſpired part of us being able to plead no immunitie or exemption, from ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from its earthly Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle; though by the light of it, it can diſcerne the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabilitie of all other things, and by the ſtrengths and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages it acquires from Reaſon and experience, can from its owne height looke downe upon all things infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to its immortalitie. The Sunne, according to its approaches, and retreats, makes all things bud, flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and decay: every thing finds their periods and diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:169925:76"/> by the force and power of that Law impoſed on it; the whole frame of Nature is in motion, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courſe of Nature in its ſeverall revolutions, <hi>Se ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turque fugitque.</hi> Arts, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, opinions, have their returnes; the ſame conduct in Princes, whether it be to act by violence, or by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell; the ſame generall <hi>genius</hi> in the people, whether the <hi>Belgians</hi> revolt under the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> or the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Invention of things, like ſome Rivers, ſometime ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in one place; and then emptying themſelves into the earth, have travel'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcovered, into places farre
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:169925:77"/> remote. Every age in part ſees the fulfilling of thoſe Propheſies of Wars, Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, Plagues; the Sceane as it were ſtill renewed to the ſucceeding ſpectators, by the turning and rowling this great Piece about; <hi>This age ſhall not paſſe, till all theſe things be fulfilled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Governments, as well as the World, containe in the matter of them appetites of diſſolution, but are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by forme, Law, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: you ſhall not tread the Stage of any Kingdome, but can afford in its Hiſtories the proſpect of its affaires diverſified with the barren Hills and Riſings of Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:169925:77"/> and Rebellions, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine falling into the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Valleyes and Flats of Peace and Tranquillitie. To recover of a Sickneſſe, is to grow young againe, ſaith the Phyſician; and bad Humors in a State diſcharg'd, is in order to convaleſcence, or long duration of Empire. Upon this Theater of the generall viciſſitude of things appeares the execution of Divine Judgements, and the wonderfull methods of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; there being many times a <hi>Labyrinth</hi> in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of it, to the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the proud reaſons of men. Make me, Lord, obey thee, in the executing thy
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:169925:78"/> Commands, though I find a reluctancie in my Will; and alſo to beleeve thee, though I find a repugnancie in my Underſtanding. Its our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections we ought to have a care of, and not ſo much a diſpoſing and ordering out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, which can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our Contents. <hi>Boetius</hi> hath elegantly deſcribed thoſe Fetters and Chaines, wherewith our affections make us undergoe the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Fortunes</hi> Wheele:</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Sed quiſquis pavidus pavet, vel optat</l>
                     <l>Quod non ſit ſtabilis, ſuique juris;</l>
                     <l>Abjecit clypeum, locoque, motus</l>
                     <l>Nectit, quâ trahi queat catenam.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:169925:78"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 46. <hi>wind,</hi> reade <hi>ruin'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 76. <hi>to ſeek,</hi> r. <hi>ſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 80. <hi>parity,</hi> r. <hi>puritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 80. <hi>acts,</hi> r. <hi>arts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 91. <hi>morions,</hi> r. <hi>motions.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169925:79"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169925:79"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
